Welcome back to another video with
ItsDrDan, and we're gonna be looking
at dehydration reactions, which
are a type of elimination reaction
of alkanes to make an alkene.
Now, what is dehydration?
Well, think of hydration, right?
Hydration is adding water to your body.
In this case, dehydrate is removing water.
So how are we going to make water?
Well, if you saw the addition
reaction video,  that was also posted
recently, water is all, has an OH
and H component that are on a chain.
So what we're going to be looking for
is looking for an OH attached to a
carbon, and then we're gonna be moving
a hydrogen from an adjacent carbon.
Now, when those are both removed, We're
gonna make H2O as a product and as a
result, it's going to make a double
bond to,  adjust for the fact that we
don't have all of our bonds remaining.
So we will have that c H two
on one carbon, and then we will
add our hydrogens to the other.
So this goes from an alkane to an alkene.
Through this elimination process.
So you can also see that it goes
from one reactant to two products.
So it's the opposite of
what we saw with addition.
Now with this, you'll commonly
also see that it has an acid
catalyst in the reaction as well.
So it could be an acid, it could be heat.
It's something that's showing
that we're having a breaking
down of our different components.
Let's look at some more
in-depth reactions.
The one really common problem that
you're given is form the major
project from the dehydration reaction.
And when you're looking at
this, you're like, oh man,
what exactly do I have to do?
So when we have this general
reaction, what we can see is we are
always given some kind of reactant.
And what we are going to be doing
is identifying the major components
that we're gonna be ripping off.
And one thing you can remember,
well, our goal is to form water, so
we're gonna be taking away an OH.
Now the question is, where do
we remove the hydrogen from?
Because you could remove it
from the carbon on its left
or the carbon on its right.
So if we were to fill in all those
hydrogens, we have 1, 2, 3 on the
right hand side, and then one.
Two on the left, where do we choose?
It's kind of a little bit of a
dilemma that we have is like, okay,
do I pick one from over here or do
I pick one on the left hand side?
So let's write down both those products.
And what we are going to do is go
through another rule to be able to
define what we, what we will have.
So it's the same idea.
We copy down our carbon structure.
And we are going to write that backbone
down because the carbons stay the same.
We're only removing the alcohol.
So the one that I have here on the,
the upper side here, this is if I
remove the hydrogen that is in orange.
So if we remove that one,
it's going to make the double
bond on the end of the chain.
If we remove the hydrogen from the
one in red, it will make the double
bond in the middle of the chain.
So you can see how there is a big
difference in both of these, right?
We have pentene on the top, and
over here we have 2-pentene.
Which will also have cis
and trans isomers to it.
So there's a big
difference between the two.
Which one will we have?
Let's look at our rule to determine which
is the correct answer, Seth Rule, which
goes through a lot of scientific verbiage
for how to describe which hydrogen you are
going to pluck off of this alkene chain.
The easy way to remember it is think
of predator versus prey mentality.
How exactly are you going
to look at these structures?
So with this, it's all about removing
the hydrogen that is more by itself.
You want to go for the weakest
link in your parent or your chain.
So you want to find the
one that's by itself.
So let's take a look at the
example we were doing before.
Let's see if we can see which hydrogen is
an easier target to remove from our chain.
So in this example, we had two
separate chains that we formed.
Now how do we tell which
one is the lower of the two?
Well, what we're gonna do is we're gonna
look back on our original structure,
and if you can see on the left hand
side, I have two hydrogens, and on
the right hand side I have three.
So the whole idea here is that we want to
pick the structure that involves the least
amount of work, which one is by itself,
which in this case you can see that
the reds structure would have only two.
So that is gonna be easier
to pluck off and to remove.
So our correct answer
for our major product.
Is going to be the bottom species.
Now, keep in mind when you say major,
that does not mean it's the only product.
It just tells you that it could be
60%, 70%, 80% of that major product, or
more, sometimes even as high as a 100%.
But it all depends on the
conditions of your reaction
and what you were doing in lab.
So 2-pentene would be our choice.
Let's go on to one other example.
So once again, if I asked you to form
the major product from a dehydration
reaction and I gave you a,  one
methyl,  cyclohexanol as an example,
what we are going to do, as before,
we are going to first identify
where we are going to remove an oh.
Now the next component is, well, where
exactly do we remove a hydrogen from?
Because it's gonna be one
of the adjacent carbons.
Next to our starred carbon here.
So if we are to star that, it
could be multiple locations.
So let's highlight them to show.
So we have one that is in this teal blue.
We have one that could be in orange
and then one that can be in red.
You have multiple options
that are available.
So let's take a look at this
particular structure and let's
go through all those options.
What ex, where exactly would
it make sense to remove?
So if we are to analyze that,
let's draw that a little bit bigger
and we will write our oh o h.
Now when we are looking at that, how
many do we have on, let's say the.
The red carbon up here.
How many hydrogens do you see?
Well, there's already currently two
bonds there, so there is gonna be two
hydrogens on this particular structure.
So we have H here and an H here.
One.
The orange structure on the
orange carbon, it's gonna be
the same general deal, right?
We have two hydrogens on each part.
And then on our last one, which was
I believe the teal blue one, we have
three hydrogens for each part, right?
So we have 1, 2, 3.
Now the question is where
would you remove it from?
Well, it's either gonna
be the top or the bottom.
They're both equally possible.
Let's draw them both and see which one
makes more sense, and let's see if there's
even a difference between them as well.
So when we go through that, we
will have our first structure.
So, and oh, I realize I could
actually draw a hexagon with this.
So we will write our first structure,
just like so, and we are going to
make a double bond on the structure
just like this with her other one.
We are gonna do the exact same thing.
We will fill in our, oh, and
write the double bond like so.
Now judging from those two
structures, is there a difference
between them or are they the same?
When you are checking these number, your
priority, so we would start from one,
two, and then go around that chain, right?
3, 4, 5, 6.
It's gonna be the same exact.
Cyclic structure on both.
It's just flipped from the other one.
So they are the same.
So these, so either one is your major
product here, and if you want to, you
could draw your minor product as well.
Uh, typically in most introductory
classes, you're never asked to
draw a minor product, but just
in case you are curious about
it, we could write that as well.
Where in this case, you're
gonna have the double bond.
On the methyl group with an,
oh, so this is minor, okay.
This would probably be less than
20% at most, um, whereas the one in
green is your major product for this,
which would be the answer on any exam
or homework and should be accepted.
Um, it all depends on your
professor or your teacher.
So depending on who, who
is teaching your class.
Definitely make sure you watch and try
to understand that, so practice it.
Hopefully this video helped you
in understanding the zeep rule.
Remember, it's all about
predator verse prey mentality.
We wanna remove the hydrogen from the
one with least hydrogens, which is
what we were doing on the structure.
We were counting our hydrogens,
removing the one from the
least to make our double bond.
Please hit that like and subscribe button.
I hope to see you for future videos
and thank you so much for stopping by.
Bye now.